Guide to the Gustav Edward Kappler papers, 1951-2014
Kappler, Gustav Edward papers, 1951-2014
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gustav Edward Kappler, papers, 1951-2014
7041
Gustav Edward Kappler, 1940-
.8 cubic feet
Photographs, manuscripts, audio recordings, ephemera.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection of color slides, tape recordings and transcripts describing the vascular surgeon's experiences during the Vietnam War.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Gustav Kappler, Cornell University Class of 1961, M.D. 1965, was a vascular surgeon during the Vietnam War.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes color slides, with a tape recording and transcript describing the slides, 1984; also a DVD of a presentation by Dr. Kappler and David Leeser given at Weill Auditorium on February 13, 2012 and a DVD with a Powerpoint presentation of the slides. Also tapes sent home, telegrams, and correspondence, 1970-1984; photograph albums; Vietnamese currency and other memorabilia; and manuscript draft for article.
Booklet compiled for the 2008 Reunion of staff from the Phu Bai/85th Evacuation Hospital, 1971/72, with information about their later lives. Folder of materials from the 2010 Reunion, including updates on their lives, CDs with photographs and songs, and information about Hilton Head.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kappler, Gustav Edward, 1940-; Vietnam War Veterans Archives.
Subjects:
Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.; Surgeons.
Places:
Vietnam.
Form and Genre Terms:
Money.; Photographs.; Color Slides.; Telegrams.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. General Items
Box 1-4
Series II. Tape Recordings
tr. 4538 to tr. 4544; tr. 5173 to tr. 5178; tr. 5179a to tr. 5184a
Series III. DVD's, CD's
Box 1: DVD-798, DVD-1150 & 1151 CD-418, CD-1643 & 1644
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. General Items
  - Patch - Regimental I-Corps (would not have been worn in Vietnam - too brightly colored) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Passport (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Love beads, Broken Peace sign, St. Martha medal (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Insignia - crest from 85th Evac. (worn on shoulder), major's and medical pins, Vietnamese commendation (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Vietnam currency (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 4 original cassettes, tr. 10158-10161 (copied onto seven reels, tr. 4538-4544) [NOT TO BE USED] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Telegrams, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Draft of article published in The Chatterbox, newsletter of WASAMA (Women's Auxiliary to the Student American Medical Association - Robin Kappler was National President) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters home, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photograph album (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Slides (5 boxes). Corrected carbon of slide talk transcript, April 6, 1984, tr. 4544 (Box 2)
  - Letters home from Cornell, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters home from Cornell, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters home from Cornell, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters home from Cornell, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Agent Orange Report, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Vietnam Commemoration, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Vietnam Veterans Memorial Fund (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Phu Bai Reunion, Hilton Head, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Phu Bai Reunion, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Group photo, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Travel itinerary, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Phu Bai Reunion, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 2008 reunion (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series II. Tape Recordings
  - Reel-to-Reel Tapes
    - Long Binh - first few days, tr. 4538
    - Phu Bai, tr. 4539
    - Phu Bai - side 1; Bob Hope - side 2, tr. 4540
    - Phu Bai later - side 1, tr. 4541
    - Phu Bai later - side 2, tr. 4542
    - Vietnam reminiscences, 3-8-84, tr. 4543
    - Vietnam slides, 4-6-84, tr. 4544
    - Gus Kappler, May 7, 1971; Vietnam War tape-recorded letters home - side 1- 3 3/4 ips; tr. 5173
    - Case, May 25, 1971; Steve Deressner - CU Roger King - M.C.V. (we trained together) Helene & Jimmy - sister Ft. Carson H (EM) CORPORECTOMY 2 Digit midget = short; softball; leisure - at last Background from Hooch Musk; Gus Kappler - taped letters home, Vietnam War - side 1; tr. 5174
    - Gus Kappler, Aug. 16, 1970; Vietnam War Tape - recorded letters home sent to the Kapplers, III San Antonio, Texas - side 1; tr. 5175
    - Gus Kappler, Aug. 1970, Nov. 9 1970; Vietnam War tape - recorded letters home - sides 1 and 2; tr. 5176
    - Gus Kappler, Vietnam War tape - recorded letters home - sisters Description - 85th, Pt. to Saigon 106 units - styrofoam Arvan - hosp. PACEX Payoffs Booby traps There 1 month Copper in background Robin - side 1; tr. 5177
    - Gus Kappler, Vietnam War tape-recorded letters home - CCN Busy OR - Vietnamese hepatectomy Bob - roommate FNG EM - enlisted man Bob building Building - Bob - side 1; tr. 5178
  - Cassette Tapes
    - Gus Kappler, May 7, 1971; Vietnam War tape-recorded letters home - side 1- 3 3/4 ips; tr. 5179a
    - Case, May 25, 1971; Steve Deressner - CU Roger King - M.C.V. (we trained together) Helene & Jimmy - sister Ft. Carson H (EM) CORPORECTOMY 2 Digit midget = short softball leisure - at last Background from Hooch Musk; Gus Kappler - taped letters home, Vietnam War - side 1; tr. 5180a
    - Guss Kappler, Aug. 16, 1970; Vietnam War Tape - recorded letters home sent to the Kapplers, III San Antonio, Texas - side 1; tr. 5181a
    - Gus Kappler, Aug. 1970, Nov. 9 1970; Vietnam War tape - recorded letters home - sides 1 and 2; tr. 5182a
    - Gus Kappler, Vietnam War tape - recorded letters home - sisters Description - 85th, Pt. to Saigon 106 units - styrofoam Arvan - hosp. PACEX Payoffs Booby traps There 1 month Copper in background Robin - side 1; tr. 5183a
    - Gus Kappler, Vietnam War tape-recorded letters home - CCN Busy OR - Vietnamese hepatectomy Bob - roommate FNG EM - enlisted man Bob building Building - Bob - side 1; tr. 5184a
- Series III. DVD's, CD's
  - 85th Evac. 38th reunion - Napa, CD-418 (Box 1)
  - Audio CD, Vietnam era music, CD-1643 (Box 1)
  - "Book list"(contains several different pdf files), CD-1644 (Box 1)
  - Battlefield trauma, DVD-798 (Box 1)
  - Vietnam combat trauma, DVD-1150 (Box 1)
  - Phu Bai Reunion, DVD-1151 (Box 1)